<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-my-document-00" ipr="full3978">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ActivityPush">Activity Streams Push Publishing
    Protocol</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2009" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a protocol for activity publishers to push
      activity notifications directly to an activity consumer. This is in
      contrast to the traditional feed-based activity publishing model where a
      consumer pulls activities from the publisher.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>...</t>

      <t>A design goal of this specification is to be compatible with the
      OpenSocial activity push mechanism, assuming that OpenSocial has been
      extended to support Activity Streams properties.</t>

      <t>This document is a work in progress. Everything here is just random
      brainstorming at this point.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Activity Publisher">An application that generates
          activities and transmits them to an activity consumer.</t>

          <t hangText="Activity Consumer">An application that recieves and
          processes activities.</t>

          <t hangText="Activity Endpoint">An HTTP resource provided by an
          activity consumer to which the publisher submits activities.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Submitting an Activity">
      <t>Before submitting an activity, the activity publisher must determine
      the URL of the activity endpoint provided by the activity consumer. The
      mechanism for doing this is not defined by this specification, but
      mechanisms may include simply providing the URL of the endpoint in the
      consumer's human-readable documentation or using the OpenID and OAuth
      integration described in <xref target="openidintegration"></xref>.</t>

      <t>An activity is submitted from the activity publisher to the activity
      consumer by submitting an HTTP POST request to the activity endpoint.
      The entity body of this request is an activity or an activity stream as
      defined by the activity streams specifications. Consumers MUST accept
      activities that are expressed in Atom as described in <xref
      target="atomactivity"></xref>, either in the form of an Atom feed or a
      single top-level Atom entry. When the request body is an Atom feed or
      Atom entry, the Content-Type header field in the request MUST carry the
      value <spanx style="verb">application/atom+xml</spanx>.</t>

      <t>A single activity submit request MAY express multiple activities,
      either by providing a feed containing a list of activities or by
      providing a single Atom entry which expresses multiple activities by
      virtue of including multiple objects.</t>

      <t>The activity consumer MAY accept any other activity serialization
      when submitted with an appropriate Content-type.</t>

      <t>If the activity consumer accepts the submitted activity, it MUST
      return an HTTP response with either a 201 Created or 202 Accepted status
      code. If 201 Created is used, the response MUST include a Location
      header which gives a URL at which the created activity can be retrieved
      as required by the HTTP specification. If the request contained multiple
      activities the consumer MUST return 202 Accepted. The response entity
      body MUST be a representation with an appropriate Content-Type of the
      submitted activity or activities as they were understood by the
      consumer. The consumer SHOULD return this response using the same
      serialization format that was used in the request.</t>

      <t>If the activity consumer does not accept all of the activities in the
      request, the consumer MUST return an appropriate HTTP error response and
      disregard all activities in the request. The consumer MUST either accept
      or reject the entirety of the request, and not accept some included
      activities but not others.</t>

      <t>The consumer SHOULD apply similar fallback behavior to submitted
      activities than what would be applied to activities retrieved from a
      feed, including the fallback behavior defined for unrecognised object
      types in the Activity Streams specifications.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="openidintegration"
             title="Integration with OpenID and OAuth">
      <t>Although this specification requires no specific mechanism for
      discovery of the activity submission endpoint URL, this section defines
      an optional integration with OpenID and OAuth to provide endpoint URL
      discovery as part of an OpenID transaction. This may be combined with
      the OpenID/OAuth hybrid extension to also provide authentication
      credentials to the consumer where necessary.</t>

      <t>TODO: Write this.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="atomactivity">
        <front>
          <title>Atom Activity Extensions</title>

          <author fullname="Martin Atkins" initials="M." surname="Atkins">
            <organization>Six Apart</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
